MICHAEL VAN NIEKERK

(+27)78 725 8846 muzimike@gmail.com

I am a senior software developer with over 6 years of experience who is passionate about writing software for good. I care deeply about writing code that helps ordinary people live better quality lives. In my spare time I enjoy film photography, learning isiXhosa, and running unreasonably long distances.

EDUCATION

Masters in Data, Economics & Development Policy (Economics), Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT)	2022
Econometrics, Political Economy, Machine Learning & AI, Microeconomics, Data Science	
Bachelor of Science (Economics), University of Cape Town (UCT)	2018
Advanced Micro & Macro, Econometrics, Labour Economics	
TESOL Qualification , <i>University of Witwatersrand Language School (WITS)</i>	2016
Bachelor of Science (Mathematics & Physics), University of Cape Town (UCT)	2015
Real Analysis, Linear Algebra, Advanced Calculus, Metric Space, Differential Equations, Numerical Methods, Computer Science	

WORK EXPERIENCE

Nov 2022 — Present LUMKANI

Senior Software Developer

Cape Town, South Africa

- Developed core features using Vue.js/Capacitor for web/app and Django/Python/MySQL for backend
- Introduced operations review with enhanced telemetry and monitoring to improve customer experience
- Transformed our ETL system into a deployable, infrastructure-as-code repository with a QA environment
- Completed a multi-year live migration off of our legacy single table DB design
- · Led a cross-team project to reduce time taken to payout insurance claims

EVIDENCE FOR POLICY DESIGN AT HARVARD KENNEDY SCHOOL

Jun 2022 - Aug 2022

Research Intern

- Cambridge, Massachusetts
- Wrote a Python CLI tool to automate repetitive, daily high frequency checks on survey responses Designed and executed a migration plan to version control all existing code in Github
- Analysed targeting of the Indonesian government's fuel subsidy policy using Stata

AMAZON WEB SERVICES May 2020 — Nov 2021

Software Developer

Cape Town, South Africa

- Automated (with the team) the migration of ~ 3000 databases from MySQL 5.5 to MySQL 5.7 without downtime
- Improved the success rate of our automated database life-cycle management (Python, Ruby, Bash)
- Audited and subsequently fixed a high severity replication risk that previously caused data inconsistencies
- Credited with ownership of high severity risk which lead to a promotion within 1st year

ACTION APPOINTMENTS

Software Developer (Part time)

Jan 2020 — Dec 2022

Cape Town, South Africa

- Rewrote the back & front end recruitment management system in Django, MySQL, and React
- Provisioned and configured Azure cloud resources (with CD) to host the new system
- Migrated all customer and client data from on-premise server to Azure and Microsoft 365 to ensure 24/7 access

ELECTRUM PAYMENTS Software Developer

Apr 2018 — Apr 2020

Cape Town, South Africa

- Popularised a RESTful testing framework and paradigm to improve reliability of production code
- · Enhanced a banking client's mobile payments service to add new features for over 10 million users
- Redesigned a banking client's user authentication system to a new, robust RESTful Java backend with a MySQL datastore
- Designed and built a new product in Java to allow clients to automate payment reconciliation and settlement

CORE SKILLS

Software Python, Javascript, Vue.js, AWS, Java, Ruby, SQL, R, Bash, Stata, Git, Docker **Knowledge Systems** Databases, data processing, modelling, econometric analysis

Communication Public speaking, critical thinking, facilitating workshops, delivering presentations, debate

Languages English, isiZulu, isiXhosa